[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net se radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
[Music]
software work OS is the modern API for
authentication and user identity it
enables B2B SAS companies to accelerate
Enterprise adoption with identity
management and complex features like
single sign on and skim built for
developers tired of using Legacy
providers like ozero work OS delivers a
unified platform with apis that can be
easily integrated and a predictable
pricing model that scales seamlessly
with your Enterprise
motion for software engineering radio
this is Sam tagert I'm here today with
Nicholas Carlo and we're going to talk
about his book Legacy code first aid kit
Nicholas is a freelance web developer
who loves building communities and
maintainable software he organizes the
software CFS meetups in Montreal Canada
and shares tips on how to work with
Legacy code on his blog understanding
Legacy code.com so welcome Nicholas Hi
Sam happy to be here with you great so
the first question is your book is
called Legacy code first aid kit how do
you define legacy
code Ah that's a good question question
so I think most people well most people
will Define legy code as some old code
which is not my definition a popular
definition of legasy code is also
Michael feather's definition which is
any code that is not tested and it's a
great definition in most cases because
in general you're working with code that
is not tested I have a slightly
different one because I want to capture
some
nuances my definition is like gassy code
is valuable code that you are afraid to
change which maybe because it's not
tested but I've seen some tested code
that would still level as Legacy and
also I like to emphasis first on the
fact that if you're dealing with Legacy
code it means that you're maintaining a
code that is impacting people it's used
in production otherwise you could just
throw it away and do over and it's
generally not a scenario so it's
valuable code in most companies there
are uccessful you will have Legacy code
that also pays for the salary so yeah I
like to think about Legacy code as you
know something you have to maintain it
may be a challenge and painful we'll
talk about that but also it can really
have a lot of impact on actual people
yeah you kind of answered my next
question which was how do you decide
when code is worth saving and
refactoring and what should be thrown
away but there is another part to that
question which is are there times when
you should take Legacy code and maybe
it's okay to just slap some duct tape on
it and keep it running as opposed to
doing a real refactoring and really
fixing it up and modernizing it
yes a lot of the answers will be depends
but I'm going to try to explain what it
depends on and what to do for rewrite
versus refactor yeah in general rewrite
is a bad ID it has been detailed in many
posts but the only moments where
rewriting the thing is a good ID is
either you're building something new so
it's actually more of a like a new
product and there is a talk from a dhh
creator of rubian rails who was like
okay but rewrites are fine Etc and when
you dig into it you realize okay he's
talking about building a whole new
product based on what you learn on the
first product in this case a rewrite is
fine the second scenario is when the
rewrite is very small uh that it
wouldn't be worth iterative approach and
that's the trick for for large systems
is to make a rewrite small enough so you
take a small chunk of for example a
monolith you take a small chunk that you
identify and your scope is to rewrite
that part and then you have strategies
in place to ship to production this new
maybe microservice along the Legacy code
base and have all of that working in
production together so in a sense you
could consider it's a reite but it's
right of a tiny chunk and that's how you
should address you know Legacy code
bases when is it not worth doing any
kind of iterative
improvement I don't know I would say you
probably need to be careful when you do
not have a test in place for instance
about the changes you are making the
first thing you will need to do when you
arrive a legacy codebase it put in place
safety nets so automated test lost
documentation lost knowledge try to
recover that monitoring also logs all of
these if they're not in place you should
start by putting them in place before
you do meaningful changes otherwise you
risk breaking a lot of stuff without
even realizing it so that will be the
scenario where before trying to refactor
the whole thing I will just do duct tape
minimal changes on it yeah I remember
seeing an interesting post where
somebody said something about if you're
going to rewrite something reimagine it
so like you know take kind of like the
dhh quote where you take what you
learned and you just write something new
that does whatever it is you do now and
I think that can be worth it too I mean
I think part of the problem seems to be
risk refactoring always seems like a
less risky option in my mind yes also
risk and we
underestimate the rewrite project
because it's like with ai ai can help
working with Legacy code basis but as a
support tool if you hope to just use AI
to refactor for example a piece of code
you do not understand the problem will
be you cannot evaluate if that's correct
and that's the same for a rewrite
because how can you tell if the new
rewrite actually does what the old
system does and there will be a lot of
surprises because all the context you
have lost it will be revealed to you and
it's better to have it revealed
progressively in small chunks rather
than with a big bang scope we had that
story so I work and leave from Quebec in
Canada and early this year the part of
the government that is responsible for
the cars and and all this so they have a
system Legacy system you can imagine and
they went to monize it and they
announced hey we're GNA shut down the
services for like three four days and we
will be back up and it's going to be
whole new and
magical and uh yeah you can anticipate
what happened it was a disaster I think
that happened in February or something
like this and it created big issues
until uh August and still today you can
see some cars driving and they do not
have the license plates because of all
of the delays that happened because of
this and they even estimated the cost of
that failed modernization project that
cost them multiple millions of dollars
because they had to pay people to work
extra hours to compensate for the new
system not working so when you talk
about a failure and a
budget like not only the budget but also
the reputation you know like people were
pissed off yeah the reite was not a good
option here yeah so my next question is
sometimes I run into situations where
management is reluctant to invest in
refactoring do you ever run into that
and why do you think that is yes yes
that's I think it's interesting because
it's one of the main complaints that
developers will have which is we don't
have time or like management won't
hellow us people just want to ship new
features and I've seen that yes the
thing is there are two reasons for that
in my experience the first one is the
failure of making a business case for
what we're doing like when we're talking
about refactoring and all this it's it's
all techn Tech stuff and we we use a lot
of technical jargon you cannot expect
you know the people driving the business
to just understand what that means and
how is that helpful for them it looks
like it's working maybe not they don't
see the value and how it connects to the
business but it does it does because if
you do nothing you will have a lot of
trouble with the business and the
developers can anticipate that they can
see it coming it's just that they fail
to communicate the importance of the
work with business work so there are a
bunch of things you can do in that area
which in general goes to try to explain
try to connect the problem with what it
will mean for the business now or later
and that if you have an organization
that has slas and slos for example
that's you have it you have your
connection here if it impacts the slas
it will impact your client it will
impact your business you can see that if
you don't have that it could be
interesting to put them in place but you
can also look at the cost of fixing the
bugs how many bugs are you fixing every
week every month how much does that cost
in terms of salaries you can look at the
opportunity cost there is a lot of
things to look into and you have to
think business like what does that means
in terms of money reputation client Etc
that technical implication so that's the
first one and the second I would say
it's the Legacy culture we talk about
Legacy code but in general like always
the problem is more often with the
people not saying that the people are
bad but they operate in a way that
doesn't help fixing the
situation for example it's very common
that the only thing that gets visible in
a company but in Tech in general it's
the makers the Explorers the new
features the new stuff always new new
new and that's the only thing we talk
about if that's more maybe an advice for
technical leaders Tech lead ctOS Etc but
if you're in a position where you can
change that culture it will be the
biggest impact you can have because if
you start making visible the work that
is essential to keep the system afloat
then more people will do it for example
if the end of your Sprint demos you save
10 minutes for mentioning the people who
are upgrading dependencies yeah just
that example for instance if you can try
to have a score of how outof dat your
system is and plot that over time with a
graph and then mention the people who
are helping move in the right direction
you will see more people interested in
doing that if you never mention it no
one will just upgrade dependencies until
they have to so changing the culture
it's something you can do if you're in a
more uh leadership position but it's
important to help your engineers make
the system more
maintainable yeah it's interesting you
mentioned dependency management I just
interviewed Scott Ford not that long ago
on freshly we'll throw that in the show
notes the other cultural thing that I've
noticed is sometimes people are afraid
to rewrite code they kind of view it as
waste like oh we wrote this and then we
learn more about the problem and now we
have to go back and rewrite it they
think oh that's a waste my opinion tends
to be well no we learned what we need so
let's go build what we need but I don't
know if you've run into that or not
yes I remember I read recently kill it
with fire from Marian Bellotti and she
addresses this she said you need to
build the wrong thing the correct way
implying that for instance
microservices are never the thing to
build first because you do not know how
your system will actually evolve if it
will evolve like I mean I worked on
system on startups and we threw away
half of the code base a few months later
so you're taking on complexity
microservices are harder to manage
especially if you only have a few
Engineers for a gain that you do not
have and that is hypothetical but if you
go with the monol through routes of
course at some point when you scale it
won't work and you will need to rewrite
it and then that's when people are like
oh that Cod base like it was too naive
who wrote that oh I did like of of
course past decisions they had less
context about the changes you need to
make today so I also try not to predict
the future too hard it's something you
can get better at when you are familiar
with the domain you are working with of
course you can anticipate where things
are going to go and if you're good you
can make future maintenance easier but I
try not to make things too complicated
up front just the thing that will work
now and for the next move and do not be
afraid of you know revisiting decisions
and rewriting a part of it or redoing it
it's also part of the job in a sense
it's successful because it means that
now you have the scalability problem you
didn't have before which is good news
because before you wanted to go from
zero to one and now you need to go from
one to 100 and that's a different thing
to do if you try to take too much
complexity at first like scalability and
and all of that over engineering you
will actually go slower and if you're at
that zero to one scale you won't be able
to try so many things so yeah I I agree
with you it's not a failure to rewrite
something in the future it's actually a
good
sign great the other cultural thing I I
see is sometimes organizations save up
refactorings and do them all in one big
push and I'm kind of curious about your
opinions on that oh yes H well it
depends first of course I I mention the
culture before and refactoring as you go
as you implement new features is
something that also should be part of a
healthy maintainable culture basically
what I like to do personally is to
refactor
something as I'm tackling a new feature
because I know what the next move is
going to be so the first thing I do is
to you know make the change easier so
that's refactoring and then the change
is easier and now we do the change and
all of that is part of developing the
future so that's great because I do a
lot of refactoring without saying to
management that I am refactoring that's
how the sausage is made and they cannot
tell the difference but I can tell the
difference at the end with the quality
of the system now a lot of refactorings
can be made like that however I've seen
sometimes problems that will need more
like we mentioned rewrite before and the
monol for instance okay at some point we
may need to do the extraction in the
microservice ETC that may be a more work
in this case it may make sense to have a
dedicated piece of it I will still try
to well in general I like to tie any
refactoring or technical work to a
business outcome because we don't do
that just for the sake of it it's
because we want to make a change for the
business at some point and this
refactoring this task enables us to do
that so it will be part of a project but
another scenario that is more frequent
is people already have this pile of
technical depth and now they are
starting to think about modernizing and
now you may have to do some you know
efforts like okay we need to spend we
had the previous company I work with
that we had what's it called
sustainability week like okay a week
every quarter the engineers will have
the time to tackle on the project that
didn't get much love for example
upgrading dependencies Etc I think it's
less ideal than having that part of the
culture of like do that every day as you
go but when you arrive in a new company
or the culture is not here it's better
than doing nothing and just wait yeah my
question would be is how sacred was that
week and how often did that week get
canceled because there was other
priorities that's a great
question no definitely definitely it
happened to be moved or to have one
cancelled but the C was not bad as
trying to make it sacred because he
managed to get the use that week for
product to think about you know the road
mapap div Vision all this which it's
clever again ideally I would rather
prefer to have not just the product
thinking about the product and the
engineers coding but to have everyone
part of that discussion you have
Engineers who know the system and how
the system is working include them in
the discussion of what the system should
do next and it will be better but again
if you're working with a legacy system
and the Legacy culture you need to start
somewhere so yeah that's those are some
great thoughts so talking about the book
a little bit more how would you compare
your book to previous books like Michael
feather's books or Martin Fowler's
refactoring
book
yeah comparing to Michael feather's book
is tough I would always recommend
reading Michael feather's book first
because it's a reference and also like
his book he really shares the mindset of
how you should approach legasi code in
general there are a few concrete
examples but he also talks a lot about
how you approach that kind of code and
this is something that I don't
necessarily tackle in my book for
instance my book will be more you're
currently stuck with a project and
you're in the trenches you need a way
out you need some techniques and what I
did was to collect the techniques I used
most frequently and to detail what they
are why they work and how to apply them
in the book and so that resulted in a
200 Pages ebook with 14 techniques but
that's more a toolbox to use when you're
in the field very versus Michael fethers
is more how you should approach Legacy
systems in general and I think you
should have both it depends you mention
Martin Fuller's refactoring book it's
probably looking more like mine in sense
of it's a catalog of refactoring recipes
so it's a book you will go back to it's
not a book you will read cover to cover
and then put on the side it's a book you
will get back to whenever you need to do
do something and you look for the
refractory move and you apply the steps
it's a bit more like my uh kit and
actually in my book I also
detail the few refactoring moves that I
use the most when it comes to Legacy
code so there is a bit of overlap but I
would say of course if you want to
become a bitter engineer in general
Martin follower's book it's a catalog of
50 plus refactoring moves it's a huge
reference so I would also recommend this
one yeah it almost feels like refactor
is like one small subset of all the
tools that you have because there's a
bunch of other tools in there too that
are not necessarily
refactorings yes I would recommend
another book actually because we're
talking about books and inspiration so
we mentioned Michael fethers we
mentioned Martin Fuller of course two
big sources of inspiration but also Adam
torill so that person if you don't know
him he wrote a book that is called your
code as a crime scene that is the most
popular one and there has been a second
edition in 2023 earlier this year but he
also wrote another book called software
design exray which is an iteration of
your code as a crime scene I would
recommend one or the other like your
code as a crime scene or software
designning xrays because it's the only
book that I know
that addresses one technique that is
tremendously useful for a legacy code
basis and this is behavioral
analysis so the idea behind behavioral
analysis is to approach your code as a
crime scene you know you don't know what
happen here you have lost a lot of the
context and the knowledge because
developers are gone there is no test
there is no docks Etc but you try to
grab what happened from
what you see and with software you have
a ton of information in Version Control
metadata like git with Git You can know
who touched what and when at least and
with that information that is in general
people don't think about this but when
you use that to combine with your other
you know static analysis tool like the
usual ones you combine them together and
that gives you a lot of things you can
do like finding which files to
prioritize in terms of refactorings
based on the quality but also how
frequently you change these files you
can also identify the part of the code
base that some of the developers are
expert in because you can see who
contributed the most to which part which
can also be useful for offboarding if
you have a developer leaving the company
could be helpful to know okay which part
of the code base do you actually know a
lot about and many other things you can
infer so I detail the hotspot analysis
for instance that is in my book is
coming from that it's something I use
frequently when I arrive on the system
and I want to prioritize what to do
especially on large Legacy systems
people are overwhelmed with everything
they could clean up and that gives you a
manageable subset of okay you should
start here and that's a plan you can
present to management because because
now you can talk about return on
investment like if we spend that amount
of time on this file we will have the
biggest return on investment for
refactoring efforts like they understand
that a little bit more it sounds like a
plan so I would recommend this very good
that was actually one of my questions
later
so so your book lists uh 14 or 15 tools
and techniques are all of them language
agnostic I tried to yes of of course at
some point it won't be so I used example
I think in my book they may be all in
JavaScript typescript I use the same
path as Martin Fuller to use a language
that is familiar with most people but I
also try to give examples in other
languages or Tools in different
languages because it it always depends
not not all languages are equal in terms
of
tooling like the net Community is
actually has a lot of advantage in in
that area also PHP has some good stuff
to be honest but it's not the case
everywhere so I try to mention other
tools that could be if the techniques
mentioning at some point you need to
touch the code so of course the way to
do it concretely for example to invert a
dependency it may depend on the language
you're working with is it more
functional is it more objectoriented is
it procedural so what I try to capture
is what to do and what you're looking
for like you want to invert the side
effect like extract the business logic
from the side effect that's what you
want to do and I show you how you do
that with ARB oriented code and with
functional code but then you have to
adapt and there are techniques that
apply yeah regardless of the language so
the behavioral analysis as long as
you're working with uh Version Control
tooling you will have that in general
it's Git You could also have that with
Mercurial if and like if you end up on
the system that is still using this
which we're talking about Legacy system
so it can happen but this will be
relevant regardless of of the uh
language and one tip I can share by the
way when you are doing hotspot analysis
you need to combine the so the frequency
of the change the churn with the code
complexity and many languages have
something to calculate the code
complexity but if your language doesn't
have you can always use the count of
lines of code for every file because
well it has been proven that it's not
super accurate but the trend of lines of
code tend to follow the trend of
complexity so you know when you do not
have any other tool that's a good first
guess yeah I really like the hotspot
analysis tool but I find I don't end up
using it a lot mostly because a lot of
the Legacy systems I encounter are not
actually in source code control so
that's like the first step so there is
no history to go back and look um so
hopefully in the future I'll uh be able
to use that a lot more but also the
thing you mentioned about doing examples
in one language and kind of have to
extrapolate them to others I mostly
program in lab view so I'm very used to
doing that because there are very few
books written in lab view most of them
tend to be Java or C or something so
next question which of the tools in the
book do you happen to end up using the
most H that's a good question well the
hotspot analysis I use it a lot when I
arrive on a project because like I'm
doing consulting so when I arrive on a
new code base I use that as part of the
tool like I talk to a lot of people and
I also use that to see if that confirms
what I'm understanding and also give me
hints of about who to ask and stuff like
this but that's situational it's not
something I would use all of the time
time when I'm coding which is the case
today the techniques I resort to the
most often are the ones about the like
refactoring the code so there are a
couple of refactoring moves that I show
but yeah inverting the dependency like
separating the business logic from the
side effects is something I do all the
time and also the automated refactorings
it's interesting because I found that a
lot of developers I've worked with they
don't know what their editor can do for
them
especially in terms of code automation
like
refactorings some people are if they
have again it depends on the language
but if you're working for example with
JavaScript or PHP or whatever and you
use intell J editor in general that
editor can transform a lot of the code
for you and it's much faster to use it
and much safer to use it rather than
trying to do the moves manually but even
sometimes like I work with people in
JavaScript script and they use vs code
so I use vs code 2 and vs code is
capable today of like renaming a symbol
across the code base automatically and
handle the renames of everything and yet
I see a lot of people just you know go
for the first occurrence change the name
and then trying to find the next
occurrence change the name and it's
super first it is slow because it takes
a while to to update all the references
and it is dangerous because you miss any
place in JavaScript you may miss some
places you have introduced a bug so yeah
automated refactoring is something I use
all the time and I find myself teaching
all the time that hey you can use this
like F2 in vs code to rename
automatically or did you know that your
webstorm can actually refactor this for
you yeah I imagine that will only get
better with AI tools now have you
noticed anything in that front does that
show any promise or is it still in its
infancy it's a big 23 topic earlier this
year I worked a lot I was curious about
this like what AI can do to work with
Legacy code and I found some promising
stuff for
example there are some tools that can
help you like understand what the piece
of code is doing I said earlier the
difficult part is how can you assess
that it's correct or not so you should
not just take it for granted but in my
experience it's a good support like it
helps you grasp a few things much faster
and if you use that combined with other
techniques it can get you code much
faster I have seen actually some
startups today are going on for the AI
is going to write the test for you I
give a little hand here and my
conclusion today is perise there are two
main problems here the first one is how
can you tell that the tests are fine or
if there is anyone any other test
missing when it's generated
automatically that's one difficult part
the second is the quality of the test
when the code is a bit complex and
things are Tangled together you need
test that will allow you to refactor
that code after if you write test
mocking everything and making everything
super rigid it's going to be difficult
for you to refactor the code after you
have the test so these are difficult but
there I have had good success with using
such a tool to find test cases that
would have taken me a long time to
realize like I don't know this piece of
code I would like to write some test
before I do anything with this and
having AI ingest that code and suggest
test scenarios for me was actually very
helpful It sped me up and
the last piece that I've seen is using
AI to refactor the code for you so you
give it Legacy piece of code tangle
spaghetti mess and you ask it hey
refactor this make it simpler and here
well yeah sometimes it may get it right
but I I tried it on things where I had
the test so I could tell whether or not
it got it right and in general like I
think most of the time it it had at at
least one issue one regression somewhere
and again the problem is when you do it
for real you cannot if you do not have
your strong test Suite before you cannot
tell so I would not use that yet unless
you have good test if you first have the
test then I could use AI to refractor
some code eventually the second thing
and this is ongoing experiment is
combining both
combining automated refactoring tools
like automated refactoring tool we will
parse the code into an as do valid
transformation to that tree and then
generate code again AI will be
generative the ID is okay maybe we can
have ai suggest refactoring moves and
connect that with your editor who can do
the refactoring moves safely and that is
interesting because I think AI can be
really good at suggesting creative stuff
especially if you're not you know an
expert in refactoring and you haven't
read all the 50 plus refactoring from uh
Martin Fuller's catalog so AI can do
that for you but you don't risk it on AI
hallucination to transform your code
base you lean on your editor that you
can trust that knows the structure of
your code across the
project yeah that's really interesting
sounds
promising so going back to the question
of which tools you end up using most I
found one of the tools I end up using a
lot almost unconsciously is the naming
can you know starting out with some name
and like generally I'm okay at coming up
with something close but usually I end
up like just as I'm doing it I'm just
constantly iterating on the name and I
thought that was rather interesting yes
this one was inspired by uh Alo belelli
he wrote a series of naming as a process
is the name of the series of lock posts
and it's interesting because the idea
like naming is hard most people will
agree with that it's a very very
difficult problem to get names right and
people try to get the name right at
first try pretty much like we said
earlier like rewriting something feels
like a failure Etc but same with the
name actually no because you learn as
you do and the more you learn the more
you can improve the names and so that's
what allo is describing and that's also
so what I picked because you can improve
names progressively in in a legacy code
base yeah I also find naming leads you
to refactorings like you end up naming
something it's like do a and b and c and
you're like oh well those are really
three concrete things maybe we should uh
extract some methods there or something
so my next questions is which tools you
think are least familiar to Developers
for working with legy code the the tools
they don't know much well in my
experience
the behavioral analysis Tools in general
like the thing I mentioned earlier with
Adam ton Hill all of that every time I
present it somewhere people are
discovering this concept so it's a
powerful concept and yet it doesn't get
as much love like every developer has
heard about refactoring from Artin
Fuller probably about the working with
effectively with Legacy code but Adam
torill that's also why I wanted to
mention him so he wrote the books he did
the
a lot of study around that some open
source code and now he has a sast
software code scene so it's free for
open- Source projects so you can try
what it can do but it's you pay for it
for a legacy project for a private
Legacy project but I think it's worth it
because you get everything that he
mentioned in one tool you can use on
your software and this is something
people don't know and yet again when
we're talking about Legacy system that
are under Version Control so sorry not
your case but if your system is under
Version Control and it's you know it's
critical it's in production used by
millions of people bringing like a lot
of money but it's all that needs to be
improved I would spend some Budget on C
scene to analyze and give you a lot of
insights about what you can do where you
should start see who knows what where
who interacts with who does that align
that the code structure aligns with your
organization also will you find coupling
between two repositories in different
languages that you were not aware of all
of that so behavioral analysis and cod
scene as a tool are not very well known
yeah I have a friend who refers to that
as code archaeology which is very
interesting because you're looking at
all the artifacts in the
repository so I think partly because I
had talked to you before I read the book
that that was actually not new to me but
one of the things that was fairly new to
me was the makato method because the
only time I've ever heard of that was
Manning I believe has a book about it
but that's the only time I'd ever heard
that mentioned how did you stumble upon
that and can you talk a little bit about
what the Mado method is yes the Mado
method it's an interesting technique I
don't use it all the time but I resort
to it when I have something to do that
is
unknown in terms of scope so more
frequent when the task to address is big
or I am new to the project so the idea
is you want to achieve something you
write it down could be on a piece of
paper you write on your objective I want
to upgrade that dependency okay that's
your target then you set a timer you try
to keep it short like 10 minutes 15
maybe but not I would not advise to do
more more than 15 minutes and you will
understand why so you started the timer
you try to complete your task within
that time box and what happens is you
will fail of course because if you could
do that within 10 minutes you wouldn't
think about doing the m method in the
first place so yeah you fail it's normal
your timer rings and you have not
completed what you wanted to do you have
maybe some work in progress or maybe
you'd have nothing and you just went and
discovered a few things about the code
so when you're at that point you should
stop you should think about where you
are what have you discovered are you
blocked what do you need and you write
it down on your paper you try to find
blockers for your main objective or
maybe you are breaking down what you
need to do into smaller parts you write
them down as nodes on your paper and you
connect them to the main node your main
objective then you pick one of these new
nodes so a subtask if you will you start
your timer again and before you start
over you get reset dash dash hard
everything if you really cannot resort
to doing that you should at least stash
everything the idea is that if you
happen to to change code in that time
box you need to revert that change
because you need to start fresh from a
fresh State on a smaller subtask
and you repeat you do that again you may
fail again like 10 minutes won't be
enough to do that subtask so you do you
repeat you write down what you found you
have a sub Sub Sub sub subtask
eventually and at some point you will be
able to complete something within this
time box maybe in two minutes you will
be able to do that little change you
wrote down and that's a different
process so at this point you're
successfully making a change within 10
minutes when you do
so you can do a comet so you will have
small comets by Design and cross it off
your
mograph the mograph is what you're
ending up with on your piece of paper or
you can use if you are using online
tools I suggest you go for a mind map
tools because they're really convenient
to draw these kind of graphs so you
cross it over and then you pick
something else that is low in the tree
the idea is that you start with the
smaller uh tasks first that are
requirements for doing the big ones by
doing the smaller ones you will finally
be able to tackle the bigger one because
all of the blockers will have been
addressed and now it's trivial to make
it done within 10 minutes and so you
really have two faces the first one is
you're discovering everything you need
to do it's like you're resolving the
dependencies of your task that wasn't
known and it's good when you do the
mograph because you have a visual
artifact of it you know that tonal
effect when you start working on
something and then you have a lot of
change going on and you don't know how
far you are from the end but you cannot
revert back to the beginning nothing is
working Etc the meograph is the solution
for this it's you're doing the same
thing but the difference is as you move
with this discipline
you have a clear view of everything that
you need to do which you can discuss
with the rest of your team because maybe
you realize that the task is too big and
you can split into smaller stuff and
eventually you have a second phase which
is okay now I'm resolving all of the
issues until the end and that feels good
because it's basically you have a too
list and you just follow it and cross
everything you can get in the zone while
doing this it's really good for the
brain so yeah in general
I would use it I told you when I'm not
sure about the scope of what I'm trying
to achieve and if I see someone in stand
up three days in a row saying I'm almost
done I know that okay that person next
time I need we need to pair a little bit
together so I will show them this
technique because that's a solution to
I'm almost done every day without any
concrete detail yeah it's one of those
things sometimes I set out to use it
like I know the task is big or I know
it's going to touch a bunch of different
pieces but sometimes I start on a task
and I think it's going to be a quick
task and if after 10 or 15 minutes I'm
like I've touched like three different
modules now and know I've got this other
thing that I don't know about I'm like
okay stop wait draw it out and it really
helps clarify things I think I find it
very useful yes but it's also very
difficult like the part where people
struggle the most it's the revert your
changes part and that's why you should
not do more than 10 or 15 minutes
because if that's 10 minutes of work
that's fine you can throw it away but if
you have been working for an hour you do
not want to throw everything away and
yet I think it's a great practice to
practice throwing away code I did that
on K but I did that on code like
following the MEO method you do that on
production code you try something it
does not work and you throw it away and
you try again and usually when you try
again it's
better
yeah very true so speaking of struggl
out of the tools in the book which ones
do you think developers struggle the
most with it's a good question I
think well I mention in the book I talk
about doing smaller comets in general
and that's an advice even if you don't
know it by the name I use like micr
committing I think that's an advice most
Engineers I've received at some point
and yet even myself like I struggled to
actually do that and the reason was
okay I know I should do small focused
comets but when I'm into it when I'm
working I do not think about doing a
small Comet it really takes a lot of
disciplines and learning the moves to
have like refa small refactoring moves
for example there are good candidates
for making a small comit you do a little
extract function you do a comet and
that's out of the way and you can
iterate I would say that's a technique
people struggle the most with in general
because they know it but in practice how
do they do that the m method is a good
solution to that because by Design the
comments you will do they will have less
than 10 minutes of work so that's one I
would say practicing refactoring move so
I mentioned a few incremental
refactorings you can do these will also
help you do smaller comets and in
general the technique I used personally
to get used to like to train myself to
do smaller comets was to use um I use a
gym timer I don't have it here but I
have a gym timer the difference with the
regular timer is that it's a timer that
buzz a set interval like every five
minutes for instance and I remember
putting that in my pocket and every five
minutes I will get a a little buzz in my
pocket and that will just remind me of
hey maybe I should stop and do a comet
maybe not but it was a nice way to have
a constant reminder while I'm working
that okay maybe I should do a small
Comet here I don't use it anymore today
because I found myself to more naturally
I have the habit of now like thinking
about hey I should do a comet but if
you're struggling taking a new habit for
example drinking water frequently a gym
timer is an actual very affordable way
of getting into a habit very cool that's
great advice so my last couple questions
are
what have you learned since writing the
book that's a good point I wrote the
book two years ago well actually almost
three and I still use most of the
techniques that I described so because I
did that work earlier this year I was
like okay from the 14 techniques am I
still like are they still relevant and
they do so that's the great stuff about
Legacy code is in general what you're
talking about still applies long time
later because we still have to work with
Legacy code bases and the concepts are
the same what I learned of course
everything that we talk about regarding
AI wasn't something in the Horizon two
three years ago so that may change there
may be new approaches and new way to
combine the traditional techniques with
like powered by AI could be interesting
then I had interesting insights about
approval testing so approval testing is
a technique I describe as a way to cover
existing code with tests fast but Emily
B actually did a couple more uh
follow-ups on this to show that you can
use approval testing also to produce new
code and this is not something I had in
mind first and I realized later that in
some occasions yes if you have a good
printer you can actually in the book I
said you should ditch this test as as
soon as you can but maybe not in some
cases it may not be the case so that
will be a change I will make that was a
misconception that I had too about
approval testing so yeah you're not the
only one no I think Dave FY also
presented approval testing the same way
in a recent video and I was like
ah you also think you should get rid of
this test but it again as usual it
depends in my experience it depends on
the quality of the printer and if you
can come up with a printer that makes
sense and make the snapshot useful from
a human perspective it's more than just
a anti- regression
test yeah if anybody wants to learn more
about approvals I did an interview with
L Ellen not that long ago that was also
on SC radio we throw the number in the
show notes very great stuff one last
question and that is have you learned
any new tool since you wrote the book
or yes I tried and failed a little bit
but something that is okay really Niche
at at this point and it's called
moldable development and you can find
the only tool I know that is doing that
today is called glamorous toolkit and
there is a small community of people
doing that
um it's a completely different way of
thinking about development you still
code
but you shape your coding environment so
your editor with code so it adapts to
whatever problem you're solving it's a
bit difficult for me to explain because
I'm not an expert in this but I've
practiced it a little bit and that's
interesting because yes indeed you can
craft like your editor serves as
documentation and visualization tool of
your codebase at the same time and I
think there is a potential here for uh
some Legacy systems because it's totally
part of what that thing can do
discovering a domain and making it
visual explaining it and as you are
discovering the domain and the code base
and the system you can build
visualizations right within your the
editor you're using and iterate from
that and then grow something the problem
is it has a cost most like I don't know
anyone who knows how to use that and
program with this it's based on Pharaoh
so like also I don't know a lot of
people are familiar with pharaoh and and
small talk but it's an easy one to grab
though so it has a huge entry cost it's
a it's something you need to learn and
it's not something small but if you're
working on a very old Legacy system that
is critical that doesn't have good
tooling for instance like if you of
course if you're talking about
JavaScript yeah you have tools for
aesthetic analysis you have tools for
dependency graphs Etc if the language
you're working with doesn't have all of
this it has a huge impact for example
you're working with health care or I
don't know Finance or something that is
not just you know Legacy web application
it may be worth it and I'm sure people
who are more experienced than me will
say no you can actually use it in much
more context for the moment my position
on it is there is a huge cost but there
is a very interesting benefit so in some
situations I may consider using that and
that's something I I wasn't aware of
when I wrote the book I would not
include it yet in the book because it's
not something I use yet but if people
want to broaden their mind and about
what's possible to do I would encourage
you to look at glamorous T kit great
thank you so much for sharing all your
wisdom with us and for writing the book
I personally have read it and I find it
quite useful and I refer back to it a
lot so thank you well thank you for
having me and I always like to share a
lot of the techniques and tips I collect
all of the tools I'm like a magnet that
tries
to grab all the resources on that topic
and then I put them on the blog and on
the book so thank you Sam for having
for software engineering radio this is
Sam tager thank you for joining
us thanks for listening to se radio an
educational program brought to you by It
software magazine for more about the
podcast including other episodes visit
our website at se-
radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack Channel at
seo. slack.com you can also email us at
team C-
radio.net this and all other episodes of
SC radio is licensed under Creative
Commons license
2.5 thanks for
[Music]